National Council of Jewish Women Collection 0009.003.001
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
National Council of Jewish Women
1910-2012
0009.003.001
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
8.5 Cubic feet 14 standard size document boxes, 1 large flat box of artifacts, 1 flat box of scrapbooks, and 2.5 linear feet of exhibit materials. Photographs are filed as part of organization photographs.
This collection consists of official publications, correspondence, flyers, newspaper clippings and other material. Of particular interest are a long run of minutes and a sampling of newsletters through many decades that provide a continuous narrative of the group for much of its history.
The National Council of Jewish Women was founded in 1893 in New York. In 1910, the Hartford Section was formed, comprised primarily of German-Jewish women from Congregation Beth Israel who were concerned with aiding the East European Jews immigrating to this country.
In 1911, the Hartford Section purchased the property at 35 Winthrop Street. Soon after, NCJW members established programs to address the needs of children living in poverty by setting up non-sectarian milk distribution stations and offering home visits by nurses.
The local NCJW sponsored many other programs. The danger of prostitution was mitigated by NCJW members providing at-risk young women with lodging, jobs and regular personal contact. NCJW offered Americanization programs to help immigrants adjust to their new home and a religious school for children in families unaffiliated with any synagogue, as well. It was the policy of NCJW to continue their activities in fulfilling local needs until the need no longer existed or until governmental or professional organizations took over the obligation.
NCJW women not only gave their own time to directly help less unfortunate. These women also recognized the importance of battling social problems at the legislative level. They championed child labor laws, low-income housing, food and drug laws, and world peace.
Toward the middle of the 20th century, NCJW undertook additional activities, such as the establishment of a scholarship fund and interfaith meetings while continuing their other long-standing programs. The NCJW responded to each new emerging social need including those of immigrant refugees fleeing Hitler.
As society changed following WWII, so did the NCJW. In 1952, an evening branch of the Hartford Section was founded for the growing population of women who worked during the day. In May 1979, the day and evening sections were joined, and all meetings were primarily evening meetings thereafter.
As immigration slowed, the immigrant aid programs were closed and the volunteers reallocated to new projects. The NCJW continued its concern for the well being of children with a troubled youth intervention program in connection with the Juvenile Court. The Council also sponsored programs for mentally challenged youth and aided fund drives for various other youth-related charitable programs.
In the 1970s and 1980s the NCJW responded to the plight of Soviet Jewry. NCJW became active in lobbying for the free passage of Soviet Jews and aided in the subsequent resettlement of Soviet Jewish immigrants in the Hartford area.
Today the NCJW continues to serve the entire non-sectarian community through legislative activism, "meals on wheels," soup kitchen support, scholarships, fundraising for children's needs both in Hartford and in Israel, and many other programs.
Scope and Contents note
Box 1: Farmington Valley Group, Hartford Evening Branch, Hartford Junior Council
Farmington Valley Group/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters
Farmington Valley Group/Service Projects
Hartford Evening Branch/Annual Reports
Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Members
Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Members/Officers, 1960s-1970s
Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Minutes, 4-1952 to 2-1953
Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Minutes, 1977-1978
Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Installations
Hartford Evening Branch/Founding
Hartford Evening Branch/Fundraising/Art Auctions and Shows
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 1940s
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs 1950s
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs 1960s
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs 1970s
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 1980s
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 1990s
Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 2000s
Hartford Evening Branch/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters
Hartford Evening Branch/Miscellaneous
Hartford Evening Branch/Newsletter, 1974 to 1979
Hartford Evening Branch/Scrapbooks -- see below
Hartford Evening Branch/Service Programs
Hartford Evening Branch/Skit, 1972
Hartford Junior Council/Annual Reports
Hartford Junior Council/Meeting Programs
Hartford Junior Council/Miscellaneous
Box 2: Hartford Section/A – Hartford Section/Board of Directors/I
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/25th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1935
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/30th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1940
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/35th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1945
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/40th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1950
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/50th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1960
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/75th Anniversary of National Organization, Hartford Observance, 1968
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/75th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1985
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/85th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1995
Hartford Section/Anniversaries/90th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 2000
Hartford Section/Annual Meetings
Hartford Section/Annual Report ("Yearbook"), 1910-11, 1911-12, 1912-13, 1913-14, 1915-16, 1917-18, 1918-19
Hartford Section/Annual Report ("Yearbook"), 1919-20, 1920-21, 1921-22
Hartford Section/Annual Report ("Yearbook"), 1922-23, 1923-24
Hartford Section/Annual Report of the President, ca 1940s
Hartford Section/Awards and Honors Given, several folders
Hartford Section/Awards and Honors Received
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Installations
Box 2A: Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Members
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Members
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Members/Lists
Box: OVERSIZE: Board of Directors/Minutes, BOUND Volumes:
Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (General Meetings), 12/1921 to 2/1933
Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (Executive and General Meetings), 5/1935 to 6/1940
Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (Executive Meetings), 3/1949 to 2/1958
Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (Executive Meetings), 6/1937 to 5/1942
Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (General Meetings), 10/1941 to 3/1958
Box 3: Hartford Section/Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Mi-Bylaws
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Meeting Agendas
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes (Executive Meetings), Misc. Dates 1951-1958
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes (General Meetings), Misc. Dates 1951-1952
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1965-1967
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1968-1969 (1970 missing)
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1971-1973
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1974-1975
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1976-1978 (1979-1981 missing)
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1982-1986
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1987-1988
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1989-1990
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1991-1992
Box 4: Hartford Section/C-E
Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes, 2005-2006
Hartford Section/By laws
Hartford Section/Calendars
Hartford Section/Conferences/Day of the Working Parent
Hartford Section/Conferences/Local members attending national triennial and training conventions
Hartford Section/Constitution and By-Laws
Hartford Section/Correspondence
Hartford section/Expansion project, 1988
Box 5: Hartford Section/Financial –Fundraising/B
Hartford Section/Financial Information/Annual Budgets, 1950s to 1980s
Hartford Section/Financial Information/Annual Financial Statements, 1940s to 1980s
Hartford Section/Financial Information/Monthly Treasury Reports, 1940s to 1950s
Hartford Section/Financial Information/Monthly Treasury Reports, 1981-1983
Hartford Section/Financial Information/Tax Exemption Status
Hartford Section/Founding
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Art Shows and Auctions
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Artist Selection
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Planning
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Planning
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Publicity
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Sales
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Auctionata
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Bargainata
Box 6: Hartford Section/Fundraising/Concerts-Meeting Programs
Hartford Section/Fundraising/"Urbanities: 1955" Musical Comedy
Hartford Section/Fundraising/85th anniversary, 1995
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Concerts
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Concerts -- Hartford Symphony
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Miscellaneous
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Stock Certificates
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Tag Sales
Hartford Section/Fundraising/Thrift Shop
Hartford Section/Grants/Pantry Grant
Hartford Section/Historical Highlights
Hartford Section/Historical Research Notes -- Miscellaneous
Hartford Section/Historical Research Notes -- Scholarship Funds
Hartford Section/Historical Research Notes – Thesis by Rachel Holtzberg on Role of NCJW in Immigrant Aid
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1920s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1940s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1950s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1960s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1970s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1980s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 1990s
Hartford Section/Meeting Programs, 2000s
Box 7: Hartford Section/Members- Miscellaneous
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Administrative Records
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Individual Members
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Committee Reports
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1940s to 1950s
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1955 to 1957
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1960s
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1970s
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1970s
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1980s
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, 1990s
Hartford Section/Members and Membership/Miscellaneous
Hartford Section/Miscellaneous
Life Members
Box 8: Hartford Section/Newsletters 1930-1979
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1930 to 1938
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1939 to 1940
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1941 to 1944
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1945 to 1950
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1951 to 1959
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1960 to 1969
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1970 to 1975
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1976 to 1977
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1978 to 1979
Box 9: Hartford Section/Newsletters 1980-2000s
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1980 to 1982
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1983
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1984 to 1985
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1986 to 1988
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1989 to 1992
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1993 to 1997
Hartford Section/Newsletter, 1998 to 2000s
Box 10: Hartford Section/Newspaper Clippings --Service Projects A-L
Hartford Section/Newspaper clippings
Hartford Section/Publicity
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Automobile emergency banner
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Blind Adults
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Chanukah Baskets
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Child Care
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Civil Liberties and Civil Rights
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Close Harmony Week
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Contemporary Jewish Affairs & Israeli Affairs
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Day of the Working Parent
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Day of the Working Parent -- Lunchbox contents
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Domestic Violence
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Girl Scout Troop #38
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Greater Hartford Shalom
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Hartford Shalom
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Hebrew University Education Programs
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Immigrants -- Early 20th Century
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Immigrants -- Soviet Jewry
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Immigrants -- Soviet Jewry
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Immigrants -- WWII Refugees
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Inflation Coalition
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Interfaith Activities
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Interval House (House Pins)
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Justice for Children Coalition
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Justice for Children Coalition
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Legislative Monitoring
Box 11: Hartford Section/Service Projects M-Z-Hartford Section/Skits
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Meals-on-Wheels
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Milk and Health Station
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Million Mom March (gun control)
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Miscellaneous
Hartford Section/Service Projects/North End Pre-School
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Religious School
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Road Shows
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Scholarship Funds
Hartford Section/Service Projects/School for Community Action
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Senior Adult Programs
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Ship-a-Box Project
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Soup Kitchens
Hartford Section/Service Projects/STOP
Hartford Section/Service Projects/Take Time to Care
Hartford Section/Service Projects/World War II Projects
Hartford Section/Shalom Book
Hartford Section/Skits
Hartford Section/SPA Committee
Hartford Section/Women who dare calendar, 1998-1999
Hartford Section/Woman of the Year/Marsha Lotstein, 1998
Box 12: National Organization: Anniversaries - M
National Organization/Anniversaries/100th Anniversary of National Organization, 1993
National Organization/Anniversaries/100th Anniversary of National Organization, 1993
National Organization/Board of Directors/Policies
National Organization/Brochures
National Organization/Conferences/10th Triennial Convention, 1923
National Organization/Conferences/11th and 16th Triennial Conventions, 1926 and 1940
National Organization/Conferences/39th Triennial Convention, 1993 (100th Anniversary)
National Organization/Conferences/7th and 8th Triennial Conventions, 1914 and 1917
National Organization/Conferences/9th Triennial Convention, 1920
National Organization/Conferences/National Day of the Working Parent, 1993
National Organization/Conferences/40th National Convention (1996)
Box 13: National Organization: Conferences - M
National Organization/Conferences/41st National Convention (1999)
National Organization/Conferences/42nd National Convention (2002)
National Organization/Conferences/Leadership Conference 1999-2003
National Organization/Conferences/Washington Institute, 1995, 1998
National Organization/Conferences/Washington Institute, 2001, 2004
National Organization/Constitution and By-Laws
National Organization/Convention 35th, 1983
National Organization/Department of Farm and Rural Work
National Organization/Miscellaneous
Box 14:
• National Organization/Newsletters – National Organization/Z
• Northeastern District
• Spare copies of anniversary program and cover
National Organization/Newsletters ”Council Woman"
National Organization/Newsletters ”Insight"
National Organization/Newsletters "Jewish Woman" (1927)
National Organization/Newsletters “NCJW Journal"
National Organization/Pennant
National Organization/Publicity
National Organization/Publicity
National Organization/Religious Materials
National Organization/Training Materials
Northeastern District
Northeastern District/Convention in Hartford, 1978
National Organization /Greater Hartford Section/100th Anniversary
Spare copies of anniversary program and cover
Photographs:
Photos/Hartford Section/Events/Anniversaries, 90th
Photos/Hartford Section/Miscellaneous
Scrapbooks: Bottom shelf
Northeastern Division Convention, May 1978
Close Harmony Week, November 1982
Hartford Section 75th Anniversary, 1985
Hartford Section 75th Anniversary/guest book, 1985
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1950s (loose-leaf)
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1964-1970, mostly Evening Branch
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1966-1968
Miscellaneous News Clippings, Flyers, and Photographs, 1970-1975
Miscellaneous News Clippings, Flyers, and Photographs, 1975-1978
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1975-1979
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1977-1984
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1980-1982
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1982-1983
Miscellaneous News Clippings and Flyers, 1983-1990
Artifacts: Miscellaneous metal badges, some of which commemorate projects on behalf of Soviet Jewry and women's issues
11th Triennial Convention Pin (1926) of Celia K. Levy (Mrs. H.P. Levy), founder and honorary president of the Hartford Section
Convention pennants and memorabilia
Ribbons signifying achievement of national support quota
Automobile emergency banner, see also Hartford Chapter
Section membership award paperweight
Membership drive stickers
Day of the Working Parent lunchbox
Printed napkins
Dice
NCJW paperclip
Life membership Achievement Award flag
Wipe-off weekly magnetic planner
Plaques from Jewish Family Service (1978-79), the Governor's Council on Voluntary
Action (1987) and Jewish Federation for Russian Resettlement work (1979)
Wise, Isidore, Executive Merchant, 11/19/1866 - 01/25/1956, Hartford, CT; Baby Milk Station; Eastern European Jews; Ellis Island; German Jews; Immigration; Jewish community relations; Jewish Women
- Series I: Farmington Valley Group, Hartford Evening Branch, Hartford Junior Council
  - Farmington Valley Group/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, undated
  - Farmington Valley Group/Service Projects, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Annual Reports, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Members, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Members/Officers, 1960s-1970s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Minutes, 4-1952 to 2-1953, 1952-1953
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Minutes, 1977-1978
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Board of Directors/Installations, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Founding, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Fundraising/Art Auctions and Shows, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 1940s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs 1950s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs 1960s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs 1970s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 1980s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 1990s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Meeting Programs, 2000s, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Members and Membership/Membership Rosters, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Newsletter, 1974 to 1979, 1974-1979
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Scrapbooks, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Service Programs, undated
  - Hartford Evening Branch/Skit, 1972
  - Hartford Junior Council/Annual Reports, undated
  - Hartford Junior Council/Meeting Programs, undated
  - Hartford Junior Council/Miscellaneous, undated
- Series II: Hartford Section/A: Hartford Section/Board of Directors/I
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/25th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1935
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/30th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1940
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/35th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1945
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/40th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1950
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/50th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1960
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/75th Anniversary of National Organization, Hartford Observance, 1968
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/75th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1985
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/85th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 1995
  - Hartford Section/Anniversaries/90th Anniversary of Hartford Section, 2000
  - Hartford Section/Annual Meetings, undated
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report ("Yearbook"), 1910-11, 1911-12, 1912-13, 1913-14, 1915-16, 1917-18, 1918-19, 1910-1918
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report ("Yearbook"), 1919-20, 1920-21, 1921-22, 1919-1920
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report ("Yearbook"), 1922-23, 1923-24, 1922-1923
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report of the President, ca 1940s
  - Hartford Section/Awards and Honors Given, several folders, undated
  - Hartford Section/Awards and Honors Received, undated
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Installations, undated
- Series IIA: Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Members
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Members, 1910-2006
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Members/Lists, 1910-2006
- OVERSIZE: Board of Directors/Minutes, BOUND Volumes:
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (General Meetings), 12/1921 to 2/1933, 1921-1933
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (Executive and General Meetings), 5/1935 to 6/1940, 1935-1940
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (Executive Meetings), 3/1949 to 2/1958, 1949-1958
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (Executive Meetings), 6/1937 to 5/1942, 1937-1942
  - Hartford Section/Annual Report/Minutes (General Meetings), 10/1941 to 3/1958, 1941-1958
- Series III: Hartford Section/Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Mi-Bylaws
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Meeting Agendas, undated
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes (Executive Meetings), Misc. Dates 1951-1958
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes (General Meetings), Misc. Dates 1951-1952
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1965-1967
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1968-1969 (1970 missing)
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1971-1973
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1974-1975
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1976-1978 (1979-1981 missing)
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1982-1986
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1987-1988
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1989-1990
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes 1991-1992
- Series IV: Hartford Section/C-E
  - Hartford Section/Board of Directors/Minutes, 2005-2006
  - Hartford Section/By laws, undated
  - Hartford Section/Calendars, undated
  - Hartford Section/Conferences/Day of the Working Parent, undated
  - Hartford Section/Conferences/Local members attending national triennial and training conventions, undated
  - Hartford Section/Constitution and By-Laws, undated
  - Hartford Section/Correspondence, undated
  - Hartford section/Expansion project, 1988
- Series V: Hartford Section/Financial_Fundraising/B
  - Hartford Section/Financial Information/Annual Budgets, 1950s to 1980s, 1950-1989
  - Hartford Section/Financial Information/Annual Financial Statements, 1940s to 1980s, 1940-1989
  - Hartford Section/Financial Information/Monthly Treasury Reports, 1940s to 1950s, 1940-1959
  - Hartford Section/Financial Information/Monthly Treasury Reports, 1981-1983
  - Hartford Section/Financial Information/Tax Exemption Status, undated
  - Hartford Section/Founding, undated
  - Hartford Section/Fundraising/Art Shows and Auctions, undated
  - Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Artist Selection, undated
  - Hartford Section/Fundraising/Artists-in-Residences -- Planning, undated